Court officer: Judgment in the matter of the
Prudential Assurance Company v Commissioners
for His Majesty s Revenue and Customs.
Lord Lloyd-Jones: Lady Simler will explain the
judgment, which was handed down on 11 September.
Lady Simler: This appeal concerns the relationship
between section 43 of the Value Added Tax Act,
which lays down rules about VAT groups and the
provisions, both European and domestic, that
deal with the time at which services or goods
are treated as supplied for VAT purposes.
Section 43 allows companies to choose to be
treated for VAT purposes as members of an entity
known as a VAT group. Once a VAT group is formed,
the business carried on by the members of the
group is treated for VAT purposes as carried
on by the appointed representative member,
and supplies of goods and services between
members of the group are disregarded so that
no VAT is payable on the intra group supplies.
The question in this case, is how the VAT group
disregard applies when between the time services
were performed and the time VAT invoices for
those services were issued, the supplier left
the VAT group. The answer depends on the proper
understanding of the effect of the time of supply
rules, set out in the Principal VAT Directive, the
VAT Act, and regulation 90 of the Value Added Tax
Regulations 1995. The VAT Act provides that VAT
on any supply of goods or services becomes due
at the time of supply. The general rule is that
a supply of services is treated as taking place
at the time when the services are performed.
There are exceptions, most relevantly here:
section 6 subsection 14, and regulation 90 of the
Regulations together provide that where services
are supplied over a period, and the whole or
part of the payment is made periodically or
from time to time, the supply is taken to
occur at the time when the supplier issues
a VAT invoice or when payment is received.
In this case, a company called Silverfleet
performed fund management services for Prudential,
when they were both members of the same VAT group.
At the time the services were performed by
Silverfleet, and when Prudential paid the
management fees that were due, those supplies were
properly disregarded for VAT purposes. However,
years later, Silverfleet stopped managing
funds for Prudential and left the VAT group,
and at that point, success fees were triggered
when the value of the funds exceeded a
contractual hurdle rate and Silverfleet
issued invoices for it in 2015 and 2016.
The issue in the appeal is whether VAT is payable
on the success fees because Prudential and
Silverfleet were no longer in the same VAT group
when Silverfleet invoiced Prudential for them,
or whether the fees are not subject to
VAT because they arose out of services
that were fully performed and in that sense,
completed while they were in the same group.
HMRC decided that VAT was properly payable. The
First-tier Tribunal allowed Prudential's appeal,
but that decision was reversed by the Upper
Tribunal and the majority of the Court of Appeal.
The Supreme Court dismisses this appeal. Lady Rose
and I give the judgment with which Lords Reed,
Hodge, Lloyd-Jones, Stephens, and Richards
agree. We sat as a panel of seven because one
of the arguments put forward by Prudential
invited the Supreme Court to disagree with
three earlier decisions of the House of Lords if
those decisions couldn't be distinguished. In the
judgment, we discussed the three House of Lords
decisions in detail and summarise their effect.
We conclude, in agreement with the Court of
Appeal, that section 43 of the VAT Act is not
a complete code with its own time of supply rules.
Instead, it must be read with section 6 of the Act
and the Regulations to determine when a supply
between members of the same VAT group took place.
The Court of Appeal was therefore
correct to apply regulation 90 sub one,
in order to determine whether the supplies
that triggered the success fees are treated
as having taken place while Silverfleet
was inside or outside the VAT group.
We conclude that the reasoning of the House of
Lords in the three earlier cases supports that
outcome. On this basis, regulation 90 sub one
has the effect of splitting the supplies made
by Silverfleet that are ongoing or that attract
successive payments into a series of separate
successive supplies, and each successive supply
by Silverfleet is treated as different in time
from the one before. In other words, the timing
of the supplies to which the success fees relate
is modified by the successive payments of
the success fees so that the services are
treated as having been supplied at the time the
invoice was issued or at the time of payment.
Given that conclusion, which was based on domestic
law only, the judgment went on to consider a new
argument raised by Prudential. Namely, whether
regulation 90, as so applied, is a permissible
domestic implementation of Article 64 or 66 of the
Directive as those articles have been interpreted
by decisions of the Court of Justice of the
European Union, decisions which predate the UK's
withdrawal from the EU. Prudential's case is that
neither article can be relied on as permitting
Regulation 90 to be applied in this way. We
agree with Prudential that Article 66 cannot be
relied on because it only gives member states the
option to postpone the time of collection of VAT
to the time of invoice or payment. It doesn't
alter or affect the time of the chargeable
event. The question is therefore, whether the
modification made by Regulation 90 sub one to
the time at which the chargeable event occurs
is a permissible implementation of Article 64.
We hold in the judgment that it is. The wording of
Article 64 is wide, and it does have the effect of
modifying the time of the chargeable event,
as well as the time of chargeability of VAT.
The judgment recognises that Article 64 has been
interpreted restrictively by the Court of Justice
in a number of cases. We discuss those cases.
However, consistently with those cases, we hold
that Article 64 can apply where the reason why
the supply of services gives rise to a successive
payment is because, as in the present case, the
parties to the contract do not know at the date
when the services are performed or when continuous
performance of the services comes to an end,
whether any further payment will ever become due
or, if it does, in what amount. In this case, it
only became clear that success fees were payable
when the contractual hurdle rate was crossed. That
was after Silverfleet left the VAT group. In
other words, Article 64 applies to supplies,
the nature of which justify payment in instalments
and can include situations where the payment for
services is uncertain or contingent at the time
the performance of the services is completed
and where the successive payment comprises an
element of payment that crystallises only once
the uncertainty or contingency is resolved.
Here, the payment of the success fees by
Prudential to Silverfleet was a successive payment
within the meaning of Article 64. Accordingly, the
answer to the question whether the services were
performed for VAT purposes at the time Silverfleet
was in the same group as Prudential is no, so far
as the success fees are concerned, because the
chargeable event to which the payment or invoices
for those fees relate was modified or postponed
to the extent of the value of the services
reflected in the later 2015 and 2016 invoices.
Lord Lloyd-Jones: Thank you.